Shippen Family Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Shippen Family Papers 1671-1936
MSS39859
Shippen family
6,500 items
26 containers plus 2 oversize
11.5 linear feet
15 microfilm reels
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Correspondence, diaries, account books, memorandum books, legal and business records, indentures, and miscellaneous papers of Thomas Lee Shippen, William Shippen Jr., Anne Home Shippen Livingston, Edward Shippen, and other family members. Also included are papers of the Nicholson family.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Byrd family.; Carter family.; Izard family.; Jefferson, Thomas, 1743-1826--Correspondence.; Key, Francis Scott, 1779-1843--Correspondence.; Lee family.; Lee, Arthur, 1740-1792--Correspondence.; Lee, Richard Henry, 1732-1794--Correspondence.; Livingston, Anne Home Shippen, 1763-1841--Marriage.; Livingston, Anne Home Shippen, 1763-1841. Anne Home Shippen Livingston papers.; Livingston, Henry Beekman, 1750-1831--Marriage.; Livingston, Margaret, 1781-1864.; Macon, Nathaniel, 1758-1837--Correspondence.; Madison, James, 1749-1812--Correspondence.; Nicholson family.; Nicholson, Joseph Hopper, 1770-1817. Joseph Hopper Nicholson papers.; Nicholson, Joseph, Jr., -1786. Joseph Nicholson Jr. papers.; Nicholson, Rebecca Lloyd, 1771-1847. Rebecca Lloyd Nicholson papers.; Otto, Louis-Guillaume, comte de Mosloy, 1754-1817.; Randolph, John, 1773-1833--Correspondence.; Roberdeau family.; Rodney, C. A. (Caesar Augustus), 1772-1824--Correspondence.; Rush, Richard, 1780-1859--Correspondence.; Shippen family.; Shippen, Alice Lee, 1736-1817. Alice Lee Shippen papers.; Shippen, Edward, 1826-1911. Edward Shippen papers.; Shippen, Thomas Lee, 1765-1798. Thomas Lee Shippen papers.; Shippen, William, Jr., 1736-1808. William Shippen Jr. papers.; Shippen, William, Sr., 1712-1801. William Shippen Sr. papers.; Short, William, 1759-1849--Correspondence.; Washington, George, 1732-1799--Correspondence.; Washington, George, 1732-1799.
Subjects
Embroidery--Patterns.; Medicine--Practice--Pennsylvania--Philadelphia.; Real estate investment--Pennsylvania--Philadelphia.; Women--Pennsylvania--Philadelphia.
Places
Pennsylvania--History--Revolution, 1775-1783.; Pennsylvania--History.; Pennsylvania--Social life and customs.; Philadelphia (Pa.)--History--Revolution, 1775-1783.; Philadelphia (Pa.)--History.; Philadelphia (Pa.)--Social life and customs.; United States--History--1783-1865.; United States--History--19th century.; United States--History--Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775.; United States--History--Revolution, 1775-1783.; United States--Politics and government--1775-1783.; United States--Politics and government--1783-1865.; United States--Politics and government--To 1775.
Occupations
Colonial officials.; Delegates, U.S. Continental Congress--Pennsylvania.; Judges; Landowners; Lawyers; Merchants; Physicians; Representatives, U.S. Congress--Maryland.
Acquisition Information
The papers of the Shippen family were deposited in the Library of Congress by Lloyd P. Shippen from 1930 to 1946 and converted to a gift in 1975.
Other Repositories
Shippen family correspondence can be located at other libraries, including the Historical Society of Pennsylvania and the American Philosophical Society, both in Philadelphia.
Related Material
Related collections in the Manuscript Division include those of Joseph Hopper Nicholson, and a number of Shippen family members. A fuller list of related collections is available under related resources at https://hdl.loc.gov/loc.mss/collmss.ms000084
Access and Restrictions
The papers of the Shippen family are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Microfilm
A microfilm edition of these papers is available on fifteen reels. Consult reference staff in the Manuscript Division concerning availability for purchase and interlibrary loan. To promote preservation of the originals, researchers are required to consult the microfilm edition as available.
Online Content
The Shippen family papers are available on the Library of Congress Web site at https://hdl.loc.gov/loc.mss/collmss.ms000084. To promote preservation of the originals, researchers are required to consult the online edition as available.
Biographical Notes
William Shippen Jr.
Date Event
1736, Oct. 21 Born, Philadelphia, Pa.
1750 Entered the College of New Jersey, Princeton, N.J. (later reorganized as the Princeton University)
1754 Graduated, College of New Jersey
1758 Traveled to Europe to study medicine
1760 Married Alice Lee (died 1801)
1761 M.D., University of Edinburgh, Scotland
1762 Returned to Philadelphia, entered medical practice there with his father, and began teaching anatomy and midwifery
1765 Began teaching surgery and anatomy at the newly organized medical school of the College of Philadelphia (later reorganized as the University of Pennsylvania).
1777 Appointed director of Continental Army hospitals during the Revolutionary War
1780 Court-martialed for speculating in hospital supplies, acquitted
1781 Resigned from his directorship of the Continental Army hospitals
1791 Joined the staff of the Pennsylvania Hospital; remained until 1802
1805 Became president, College of Physicians of Philadelphia
1808, July 11 Died, Philadelphia, Pa.
Ann ("Nancy") Home Shippen Livingston
Date Event
1763, Feb. 24 Born, Shippensburg, Pa.
1781 Engaged to Louis-Guillaume Otto of the French delegation in Philadelphia. Married, and separated from, Henry Beekman Livingston Birth of daughter Margaret ("Peggy") Beekman Livingston
1783 Shared custody of Peggy Livingston with Livingston family after Peggy went to live with her Livingston grandmother in New York
1841, Aug. 25 Died, Philadelphia, Pa.
Thomas Lee Shippen
Date Event
1765 Born, Philadelphia, Pa.
1784 Returned to Philadelphia after studying law in Williamsburg, Va.
1785 1789 Traveled in Europe; met Thomas Jefferson in Paris and received advice from him about travel; studied law at the Middle Temple, London
1789 Returned to Philadelphia
1791 Married Elizabeth Carter Farley Bannister
1798, Feb. 4 Died, Charleston, S.C.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of the Shippen family span the years 1671-1936. They consist of correspondence, diaries, account books, memorandum books, legal and business papers, indentures, and miscellaneous papers. Family members primarily represented include William Shippen Jr. (1736-1808); his wife Alice Lee Shippen (1736-1817); their children Anne ("Nancy") Home (or Hume) Shippen Livingston (1763-1841) and Thomas Lee Shippen (1765-1798); and William's father, William Shippen Sr. (1712-1801) Papers of the Nicholson family (1671-1860) are also included. The collection is organized in six series: Diaries and Journals, Correspondence, Family Papers, Miscellany, Nicholson Family Papers, and Oversize.
The papers chiefly document the family of William Shippen Jr. They reflect the family’s experiences during the Revolutionary War, their participation in the Philadelphia social circle that surrounded George Washington during his presidency, and the family’s engagement with national politics. They cover William Shippen Jr.’s medical practice, the family’s dealings in Philadelphia real estate, the administration of family estates, and the private lives of family members. The papers are notable for their documentation of the lives of the women of the family, in diaries, letters, and such ephemera as embroidery patterns. Correspondence with and material from members of the Carter, Lee, Nicholson, Roberdeau, other families, some of whom are related, is included.
Correspondents of note include Thomas Jefferson, Francis Scott Key (to Rebecca Nicholson), James Madison (1749-1812), Richard Rush (who appears to have administered the estates of William Shippen Jr. and his son, Thomas Lee Shippen), William Short, and George Washington (two letters to William Shippen Jr, May 3, 1777, and May 7, 1789).
Ann ("Nancy") Home Shippen Livingston’s life is documented by diaries, correspondence, and letterbooks. These document her romance with French diplomat Louis-Guillaume Otto, comte de Mosloy, her unhappy marriage to Henry Beekman Livingston, her separation from Livingston and loss of custody of her child, Margaret "Peggy" Beekman Livingston, her observations on women’s position in society, her life in and around Philadelphia, travels to New York to see her daughter, and more. Her correspondence is with her parents, husband, daughter, uncles Arthur Lee and Richard Henry Lee, and members of the Livingston family.
The diaries and correspondence of Thomas Lee Shippen document his travels in Europe during the 1780s, and subsequent family life until his death in 1798. Correspondence of his wife, Elizabeth Carter (Farley) Bannister Shippen, is also included. (A young widow at the time of their marriage, Elizabeth Shippen married George Izard after Thomas Lee Shippen's death.) Thomas Lee Shippen’s correspondence includes letters from Thomas Jefferson advising him on his European travels, including a detailed itinerary, dated June 19, 1788. There is substantial correspondence on political and family topics between members of the family and Alice Lee Shippen’s brothers, particularly diplomat Arthur Lee and Revolutionary War figure and United States Senator Richard Henry Lee. Alice Lee Shippen’s correspondence is largely to her children and to her niece, Lucy Carter.
Also included is a substantial group of papers of Joseph Hopper Nicholson (1770-1817), a Maryland congressman (1799-1806) and subsequently a judge; his wife, Rebecca Lloyd Nicholson; father, Joseph Nicholson Jr., and other members of their family. Joseph Hopper Nicholson’s correspondence includes letters from congressional colleagues, including Nathaniel Macon, John Randolph, and C. A. Rodney. There are also letters from Frances Few, niece of Hannah Nicholson Gallatin and Albert Gallatin.
Two oversized account books, 1763-1776 and 1776-1793, maintained by William Shippen Jr., contain, among his routine household accounts, records of his medical practice, including purchases of drugs and payments from patients with brief notes on their conditions. Shippen’s correspondence includes letters concerning his hospital post during the Revolutionary War, and exchanges with his children, Edward Shippen, and others.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in six series:
Diaries and Journals, 1783-1890
Correspondence, 1776-1817
Family Papers, 1754-1936
Miscellany, 1693-1875
Nicholson Family Papers, 1671-1860
Oversize, 1759-1793
Container List
Available on microfilm. Shelf no. 14,051
- Diaries and Journals, 1783-1890 (Box 1-2, Reel 1-2)
  Diaries, journals, memorandum books, and account books of family members Ann ("Nancy") Shippen Livingston, Howard Post, Mary Elizabeth Roberdeau, Edward Shippen, and Thomas Lee Shippen.
  Arranged by name of family member and therein by type of material and chronologically.
  - Shippen, Thomas Lee (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Diaries kept during stay in Europe, 1786-1789, (7 vols.) (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Journals of travels in Europe, 1788 (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Journal of travels to Ireland and Italy, 1788-1789 (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Diaries, 1795-1797, (7 vols.) (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Account books, 1786, 1791-1797 (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Memorandum book, 1791 (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - Livingston, Anne Home Shippen, diaries, 1783-1812 (Box 2, Reel 2)
  - Shippen, Edward, diaries, 1888-1890 (Box 2, Reel 2)
  - Post, Howard, songbooks, memorandum books, 1880, 1885 (Box 2, Reel 2)
  - Roberdeau, Mary Elizabeth, legal notebook, undated (Box 2, Reel 2)
  - Miscellaneous memorandum books, 1811-1824 (Box 2, Reel 2)
- Correspondence, 1776-1817 (Box 2, Reel 2-3)
  Letters received by members of the Cutting, Farley, Lee, and Shippen families. Includes letters from Francis Scott Key, Lord Lansdowne, Arthur Lee, Richard Henry Lee, James Madison (1749-1812), and George Washington.
  Arranged by name of correspondent and therein chronologically.
  - Carter, M. C., 1814 (Box 2, Reel 2)
  - Cutting, John B., Arthur Lee, and William Short, 1787-1788 (Box 2, Reel 2)
  - Byrd and Carter family letters, 1814-1817 (Box 2, Reel 2)
  - Jefferson, Thomas, letters and travel notes, 1785-1789 (Box 2, Reel 2)
  - Key, Francis Scott, 1815-1817 (Box 2, Reel 2)
  - Lansdowne, Lord, 1786-1788 (Box 2, Reel 2)
  - Lee, Arthur, 1779-1992 (Box 2, Reel 2)
  - Lee, Richard Henry, 1776-1794, (7 folders) (Box 2, Reel 3)
  - Lee, Lud., Francis Lightfoot Lee, C. Lee, Richard Henry Lee, and William Lee, 1783-1787, undated (Box 2, Reel 3)
  - Madison, James (1749-1812), C. Lee, 1791 (Box 2, Reel 3)
  - Washington, B., 1784 (Box 2, Reel 3)
  - Washington, George, 1777, 1789 (Box 2, Reel 3)
  - Unidentified, undated (Box 2, Reel 3)
- Family Papers, 1754-1936 (Box 3-15, Reel 3-10)
  Correspondence, memorandum books, financial and legal documents, and miscellaneous material chiefly of members of the family of William Shippen Jr, including Alice Lee Shippen, Ann Home Shippen Livingston, Thomas Lee Shippen, and others.
  Arranged by name of family member and therein by type of material.
  - Shippen, William, Sr., deed of partition, indenture, and will, 1802 (Box 3, Reel 3)
  - Shippen, William, Jr., correspondence, 1754-1808 (Box 3, Reel 3)
  - Shippen, William, Jr., estate of, 1808-1811 (Box 3, Reel 3)
  - Shippen, William, Jr., miscellaneous papers, 1754-1809, undated (Box 3, Reel 3)
  - Shippen, Alice Lee (wife of William Jr.), correspondence, 1811-1816, undated (Box 3, Reel 3)
  - Livingston, Anne Home Shippen (Box 4, Reel 3)
    - Correspondence (Box 4, Reel 3)
      - 1773-1801 (Box 4, Reel 3)
      - 1783-1820, undated (Box 4, Reel 3)
    - Letterbooks (Box 4, Reel 3)
      - 1786-1789, undated (Box 4, Reel 3)
      - 1790-1794 (Box 5, Reel 3)
    - Miscellany, 1816, 1832, undated (Box 5, Reel 3)
  - Livingston, Margaret B., miscellany (Box 5, Reel 4)
  - Shippen, Thomas Lee (Box 5, Reel 4)
    - Correspondence with father (William Jr.) (Box 5, Reel 4)
      - 1779-1788, undated (Box 5, Reel 4)
      - 1786-1797, undated (Box 6, Reel 4)
    - Letters to wife, father, and sister, 1790-1793 (Box 6, Reel 4)
    - Letters to sister, 1779-1794 (Box 6, Reel 4)
    - Correspondence, 1781-1798 (Box 7, Reel 5)
    - Letterbook, 1786-1789 (Box 7, Reel 5)
    - Memoranda books, 1779-1796 (Box 7, Reel 5)
  - Shippen, Elizabeth Carter Farley Bannister (wife of Thomas Lee Shippen), correspondence, 1791-1802, undated (Box 8, Reel 5)
  - Izard, Elizabeth Carter Farley Shippen (wife of George Izard), letters to son William, 1806-1826 (Box 8, Reel 5)
  - Shippen, Ann, letters to Elizabeth Carter Farley Bannister (wife of Thomas Lee Shippen), 1798-1801 (Box 8, Reel 5)
  - Shippen, Thomas Lee, Jr., letters from Princeton, N.J., 1808-1809 (Box 9, Reel 6)
  - Shippen, William, III (Box 9, Reel 6)
    - Correspondence (Box 9, Reel 6)
      - 1806-1817 (Box 9, Reel 6)
      - 1818-1825 (Box 10, Reel 6)
      - 1826-1842 (Box 11, Reel 7)
      - 1843-1850, undated (Box 12, Reel 7)
    - Letters and papers, 1810-1857, undated (Box 12, Reel 7)
    - Legal papers (Box 12, Reel 7)
      - 1826-1848 (Box 12, Reel 7)
      - 1849-1856, undated (Box 13, Reel 8)
    - Memorandum books, 1832-1834 (Box 13, Reel 8)
    - Miscellaneous receipts, 1850s (Box 13, Reel 8)
  - Shippen, Mary Louisa Shore (wife of William III), correspondence, 1799-1832, undated (Box 13, Reel 8)
  - Shippen, Thomas Lee, III, correspondence, 1843-1849 (Box 13, Reel 8)
  - Shippen, Edward (Box 13, Reel 8)
    - Correspondence, 1851-1895, undated (Box 13, Reel 8)
    - Miscellaneous papers (Box 13, Reel 8)
    - Letters to Miss McElroy, 1866-1867 (Box 14, Reel 9)
  - Shippen, Mrs. Edward, correspondence, 1882-1916 (Box 14, Reel 9)
  - Shippen, Lloyd P., letters from Ethel Armes, 1934-1936 (Box 15, Reel 10)
  - Shippen, Joseph, to Elizabeth Harmer, 1776 (Box 15, Reel 10)
- Miscellany, 1693-1875 (Box 15-21, Reel 10-12)
  Financial and legal records, miscellaneous correspondence, genealogical material, memorabilia, poetry, printed matter, and other miscellaneous items.
  Arranged alphabetically by type of material.
  - Accounts, 1734-1804 (Box 15, Reel 10)
  - Miscellaneous and Thomas Lee Shippen correspondence, 1763-1825 (Box 15, Reel 10)
  - Deeds, indentures, and related matter (Box 15, Reel 10)
    - 1693-1748 (Box 15, Reel 10)
    - 1693-1748 (Box 16, Reel 10)
    - 1750-1787 (Box 17, Reel 11)
    - 1788-1854, undated (Box 18, Reel 11)
  - Deeds and wills (Box 19, Reel 11)
  - Estate of Edward Wharton (Box 19, Reel 11)
  - Embroidery patterns (Box 19, Reel 11)
  - Financial papers, 1790-1839 (Box 19, Reel 11)
  - Genealogical material (Box 20, Reel 12)
  - Memorabilia (Box 20, Reel 12)
  - Newspapers (Box 20, Reel 12)
  - Miscellaneous papers, 1784-1875, undated (Box 20, Reel 12)
  - Photographs (Box 20, Reel 12)
  - Poems (Box 20, Reel 12)
  - Printed matter and miscellaneous correspondence (Box 21, Reel 12)
  - “The Star Spangled Banner” and memorabilia (Box 21, Reel 12)
- Nicholson Family Papers, 1671-1860 (Box 21-26, Reel 12-15)
  Chiefly correspondence with some legal material and miscellany.
  - Lloyd, Rebecca, correspondence, 1788-1792, undated (Box 21, Reel 12)
  - Nicholson, Rebecca Lloyd (wife of Joseph Hopper) (Box 21, Reel 12)
    - Correspondence (Box 21, Reel 12)
      - 1793-1818 (Box 21, Reel 12)
      - 1819-1847, undated (Box 22, Reel 13)
      - Undated (Box 23, Reel 13)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence and papers, 1781-1836, undated (Box 23, Reel 13)
  - Nicholson, Joseph, Jr., correspondence, 1730-1788 (Box 23, Reel 13)
  - Nicholson, Joseph H. (Box 23, Reel 13)
    - Correspondence (Box 23, Reel 13)
      - 1779, 1793-1799 (Box 23, Reel 13)
      - 1799-1815 (Box 24, Reel 14)
      - 1816-1817, 1786-1808 (Box 25, Reel 14)
    - Extracts of cases argued, 1813, undated (Box 25, Reel 14)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 25, Reel 14)
  - Nicholson, James Macon, correspondence, 1817-1848, undated (Box 26, Reel 15)
  - Nicholson, Ainthia Darby Parker (wife of James Macon), correspondence, 1854-1860 (Box 26, Reel 15)
  - Nicholson, Joseph H., Esq., correspondence, 1843-1857 (Box 26, Reel 15)
  - Nicholson miscellany, 1671-1814, undated (Box 26, Reel 15)
  - Nicholson photograph of portrait, circa 1810 (Box 26, Reel 15)
- Oversize, 1759-1793 (Box 27-28, Reel 15)
  Three volumes containing financial records and patient records, kept by William Shippen Sr. and his son, William Shippen Jr.
  Arranged by size.
  - Account book labeled Q, circa 1759-1765 (Box 27, Reel 15)
  - Account book of William Shippen Sr., 1763-1776 (Box 27, Reel 15)
  - Account book labeled C [William Shippen Jr.], circa 1775-1793 (Box 28, Reel 15)